<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The effect of certaine branches of the statute made in anno 33. Henrici viij. touching the maintenance of artillery, and the punishment of such as vse vnlawfull games, very necessary to be put in execution.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc. (Public general acts). Abridgments</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12978</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99892697</idno>
  <idno type="VID">188362</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248561297</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">STC 8892</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 1851.b.3[11]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123873</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99892697</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99892697e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12978)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 188362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C10:2[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The effect of certaine branches of the statute made in anno 33. Henrici viij. touching the maintenance of artillery, and the punishment of such as vse vnlawfull games, very necessary to be put in execution.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc. (Public general acts). Abridgments</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Bonham Norton and Iohn Bill, printers to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XXVIII. [1628]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An abridgment of Public General Act 33 Hen.VIII.c.9, reissued periodically in an attempt at enforcement.</note>
                  <note>Arms 23, with 1 leaf below the lion's leg; Steele notation: and house hundred.  55 lines.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Archery --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Bow and arrow --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Games --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:188362:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>¶ The effect of certaine branches of the Statute made in Anno 33. Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici viij. touching the maintenance of Artillery, and the punishment of such as vse vnlawfull games, very necessary to be put in execution.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FIrst, that all Fathers, Gouernours, and rulers of such as be tender of age, doe teach and</hi> bring them vp in the knowledge of Shooting, and that euery man hauing a man childe, or men children in his house, shall prouide, ordaine, and haue in his house for euery man child, being of the age of seuen yeeres and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, till he shall come to the age of seuenteene yeeres, a Bow and two shafts, to induce and learne them, and bring them vp in Shooting, and shall deliuer all the same Bow and Arrowes to the same yong men to vse and occupy. And if the same yong men be seruants, that then their master shall abate the mony that they shall pay for the same Bowes and Arrowes of their wages. And after all such yong men shall come to the age of seuenteene yeeres, euery of them shall prouide &amp; haue a Bow and foure Arrowes continually for himselfe, at his proper cost and charges, or else of the gift or prouision of his friends, and vse and occupie the same in Shooting, as is before rehearsed. And if the master suffer any of his seruants taking wages, being in his houshold, and vnder the age of seuenteene yeeres, to lacke a Bow and two Arrowes, contrary to the forme of this Estatute, by the space of one moneth together, then the master or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in whom such negligence shall be, shall for euery such default forfeit vi.s.viii.d. And that euery seruant, passing the age of seuenteene yeeres, and vnder the age of threescore yeeres, and taking wages, which can, or is able to Shoot, and shall lacke a Bow and foure Arrowes by the space of one moneth together, shall for euery such default forfeit and lose vi.s. viii.d.</p>
            <p>ITem, that no person by himselfe, Factor, Deputy, seruant, or other person, shall for his or their gaine, lucre, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, keepe, haue, hold, occupy, exercise, or maintaine any common house, Alley, or place of Bowling, Coiting, Cloise, Coiles, halfe bowle, Tennis, Dicing, Table, or Carding, or any other manner of Game, prohibited by any Statute heretofore made or any vnlawfull new game now inuented or made, or hereafter to be inuented, found, had, or made, vpon paine to forfeit and pay for euery day, keeping, hauing, maintaining, or suffering any such game to be had, kept, executed, played, or maintained within any such House, Garden, Alley, or other place, contrary to the forme and effect of this Estatute, xl.s. and the players so taken, to pay for euery time vi.s.viii.d.</p>
            <p>ITem, That the Iustices of Peace, and euery Maior Sheriffe, Bailiffe, Constable, or other head Officer, haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to enter into all places, aswell within Franchises or elsewhere, and the persons offending in any of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses, to take and put in prison, vntill such time they put in Sureties no more to suffer, occupy, or commit the said offences.</p>
            <p>ITem, That all Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, Constables, and other head. Officers within euery City, Borough, and Towne within this Realme, where any such Officers shall fortune to bee, aswell within the Franchises as without, shall make due search weekely, or at the furthest at all times heereafter once euery Moneth in all places, where any such Houses, Alleys, Play or Players shall be suspected to be had, kept, and maintained. And if the sayd Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, Constables, and other head Officers, within their Cities, Boroughs, and Townes, aswell within Franchises as without, doe not make due search at the furthest once euery Moneth, if the case so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, according to the tenor of this Act, and doe not execute the same in all things, according to the purport and force of the same: that then euery such Maior, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, Constables, or other head Officer, to pay and forfeit for euery Moneth not making such search, nor executing the same, xl.s.</p>
            <p>ITem, That no Artificer, or handicrafts man of any occupation, Husbandman, Apprentice, Labourer, seruant of Husbandry, Iourney man, or seruant, or Artificer, Mariner, Fisherman, Waterman, or any Seruing man, may vse any vnlawfull Game.</p>
            <p>ITem, That all that play at Bowles, or any other vnlawfull Game in the fields, to lose for euery such time vi.s. viii.d. and to be committed to prison, vnto such time they put in Sureties no more to vse the same.</p>
            <p>ITem, This Statute to bee proclaimed foure times euery yeere, and the like to be done in all Assises and Sessions, and to continue for euer.</p>
            <p>ITem, it is not the intent of the Statute, that they shall onely buy Bow and Arrowes, but the Constables, or other head officers to call them, and see they doe vse shooting monethly, if the cause so require, or else hee shall forfeit euery moueth xl.s.</p>
            <p>ITem for euery three moneths that the Buttes are out of repayre, they doe forfeit to the King, and him that shall sue for it, xx s.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MEmorandum,</hi> That there is a Prouiso in this Statute, for all men of worship, which may dispend one hundred pounds yeerely and vpwards, may vse these games with discretion at their pleasures.</p>
            <p>The Messengers Fee for declaring these Branches, twelue pence.</p>
            <closer>God saue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by BONHAM NORTON and IOHN BILL, Printers to the Kings most Excellent MAIESTIE. M.DC.XXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>